The following content is
provided under a Creative
Commons license.
Your support will help
MIT OpenCourseWare
continue to offer high quality
educational resources for free.
To make a donation or
view additional materials
from hundreds of MIT courses,
visit MIT OpenCourseWare
at ocw.mit.edu.
PROFESSOR: OK, so
good afternoon.
Today, we will review
probability theory.
So I will mostly focus on-- I'll
give you some distributions.
So probabilistic distributions,
that will be of interest to us
throughout the course.
And I will talk about
moment-generating function
a little bit.
Afterwards, I will talk
about law of large numbers
and central limit theorem.
Who has heard of all
of these topics before?
OK.
That's good.
Then I'll try to focus
more on a little bit more
of the advanced stuff.
Then a big part of it
will be review for you.
So first of all, just to
agree on terminology, let's
review some definitions.
So a random variable
X-- we will talk
about discrete and
continuous random variables.
Just to set up the notation,
I will write discrete as X
and continuous random
variable as Y for now.
So they are given by its
probability distribution--
discrete random variable is
given by its probability mass
function, f sub
X, I will denote.
And continuous is given by
probability distribution
function.
I will denote by f
sub Y. So pmf and pdf.
Here, I just use a
subscript because I
wanted to distinguish
f sub x and f sub y.
But when it's clear which random
variable we're talking about,
I'll just say f.
So what is this?
A probability mass function is
a function from the sample space
to non-negative reals such
that the sum over all points
in the domain equals 1.
The probability distribution
is very similar.
The function from the
sample space non-negative
reals, but now the
integration over the domain.
So it's pretty much safe to
consider our sample space
to be the real numbers for
continuous random variables.
Later in the course, you
will see some examples where
it's not the real numbers.
But for now, just consider
it as real numbers.
For example, probability
mass function.
If X takes 1 with
probability 1/3,
minus 1 with probability 1/3,
and 0 with probability 1/3.
Then our probability mass
function is f_x(1) equals
f_x(-1), 1/3, just like that.
An example of a
continuous random variable
is if-- let's say, for
example, if f sub Y is
equal to 1 for all
y in [0,1], then
this is pdf of uniform
random variable
where the space is [0,1].
So this random variable
just picks one out
of the three numbers
with equal probability.
This picks one out of this,
all the real numbers between 0
and 1, with equal probability.
These are just some basic stuff.
You should be
familiar with this,
but I wrote it down just so
that we agree on the notation.
OK.
Both of the boards don't slide.
That's good.
A few more stuff.
Expectation-- probability first.
Probability of an event can be
computed as probability of A
is equal to either sum of all
points in A-- this probability
mass function-- or
integral over the set A
depending on what you're using.
And expectation, or mean
is-- expectation of X
is equal to the sum over
all x, x times that.
And expectation of Y is
the integral over omega.
Oh, sorry.
Space.
y times.
OK.
And one more basic
concept I'd like to review
is two random variables X_1, X_2
are independent if probability
that X_1 is in A and
X_2 is in B equals
the product of the
probabilities, for all events A
and B. OK.
All agreed?
So for independence, I will
talk about independence
of several random
variables as well.
There are two concepts
of independence--
not two, but several.
The two most popular are
mutually independent events
and pairwise independent events.
Can somebody tell me the
difference between these two
for several variables?
Yes?
AUDIENCE: So
usually, independent
means all the random
variables are independent,
like X_1 is independent
with every others.
But pairwise means X_1
and X_2 are independent,
but X_1, X_2, and x_3, they
may not be independent.
PROFESSOR: OK.
Maybe-- yeah.
So that's good.
So let's see-- for the example
of three random variables,
it might be the case that
each pair are independent.
X_1 and X_2 X_1 is
independent with X_2,
X_1 is independent with
X_3, X_2 is with X_3.
But altogether, it's
not independent.
What that means is, this type
of statement is not true.
So there are say A_1, A_2, A_3
for which this does not hold.
But that's just some
technical detail.
We will mostly just consider
mutually independent events.
So when we say that several
random variables are
independent, it just means
whatever collection you take,
they're all independent.
OK.
So a little bit more fun
stuff [? in this ?] overview.
So we defined random variables.
And one of the most
universal random variable,
or distribution, is a
normal distribution.
It's a continuous
random variable.
Our continuous random variable
has normal distribution,
is said to have normal
distribution, if-- N(mu,
sigma)-- if the probability
distribution function is given
as 1 over sigma
square root 2 pi,
e to the minus x
minus mu squared.
For all reals.
OK?
So mu mean over--
that's one of the most
universal random variables--
distributions, the most
important one as well.
OK.
So this distribution, how
it looks like-- I'm sure
you saw this bell curve before.
It looks like this if
it's N(0,1), let's say.
And that's your y.
So it's centered
around the origin,
and it's symmetrical
on the origin.
So now let's look
at our purpose.
Let's think about our purpose.
We want to model a financial
product or a stock,
the price of the stock,
using some random variable.
The first thing you can try
is to use normal distribution.
Normal distribution
doesn't make sense,
but we can say the price at
day n minus the price at day n
minus 1 is normal distribution.
Is this a sensible definition?
That's not really.
So it's not a good choice.
You can model it like this,
but it's not a good choice.
There may be several
reasons, but one reason
is that it doesn't take into
account the order of magnitude
of the price itself.
So the stock-- let's say
you have a stock price that
goes something like that.
And say it was $10
here, and $50 here.
Regardless of where
your position is at,
it says that the increment,
the absolute value of increment
is identically distributed at
this point and at this point.
But if you observed
how it works,
usually that's not
normally distributed.
What's normally distributed
is the percentage
of how much it changes daily.
So this is not a sensible
model, not a good model.
But still, we can use
normal distribution
to come up with a
pretty good model.
So instead, what we want
is a relative difference
to be normally distributed.
That is the percent.
The question is, what is
the distribution of price?
What does the
distribution of price?
So it's not a very
good explanation.
Because I'm giving just
discrete increments while
these are continuous
random variables and so on.
But what I'm trying to say here
is that normal distribution
is not good enough.
Instead, we want the
percentage change
to be normally distributed.
And if that is the case,
what will be the distribution
of the random variable?
In this case, what will be
the distribution of the price?
One thing I should
mention is, in this case,
if each discrement is
normally distributed,
then the price at
day n will still
be a normal random variable
distributed like that.
So if there's no tendency-- if
the average daily increment is
0, then no matter
how far you go,
your random variable will
be normally distributed.
But here, that will
not be the case.
So we want to see what
the distribution of P_n
will be in this case.
OK.
To do that-- let me formally
write down what I want to say.
What I want to say is this.
I want to define a
log-normal distribution Y,
or log-normal random variable
Y, such that log of Y
is normally distributed.
So to derive the probability
distribution of this
from the normal
distribution, we can
use the change of
variable formula, which
says the following:
suppose X and Y
are random variables such
that-- probability of X
minus x-- for all x.
Then F of Y of y--
the first-- of f
sub X is equal to f sub Y of y.
h of x.
So let's try to fit
into this story.
We want to have a
random variable Y such
that log Y is
normally distributed.
Here-- so you can
put log of x here.
If Y is normally distributed,
X will be the distribution
that we're interested in.
So using this formula, we can
find probability distribution
function of the log-normal
distribution using
the probability
distribution of normal.
So let's do that.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE], right?
PROFESSOR: Yes.
So it's not a good choice.
Locally, it might
be good choice.
But if it's taken
over a long time,
it won't be a good choice.
Because it will also take
negative values, for example.
So if you just take
this model, what's
going to happen over
a long period of time
is it's going to hit
this square root of n,
negative square root of
n line infinitely often.
And then it can
go up to infinity,
or it can go down to
infinity eventually.
So it will take negative
values and positive values.
That's one reason, but
there are several reasons
why that's not a good choice.
If you look at a
very small scale,
it might be OK, because the base
price doesn't change that much.
So if you model
in terms of ratio,
our if you model it
in an absolute way,
it doesn't matter that much.
But if you want to do it a
little bit more large scale,
then that's not a
very good choice.
Other questions?
Do you want me to
add some explanation?
OK.
So let me get this right.
Y. I want X to be-- yes.
I want X to be the log
normal distribution.
And I want Y to be
normal distribution
or a normal random variable.
Then the probability
that X is at most x
equals the probability
that Y is at most-- sigma.
Y is at most log x.
That's the definition of
log-normal distribution.
Then by using this change
of variable formula,
probability density
function of X
is equal to probability
density function of Y at log
x times the differentiation
of log x which is 1 over x.
So it becomes 1 over
x sigma square root
2 pi, e to the minus
log x minus mu squared.
So log-normal
distribution can also
be defined as the
distribution which has
probability mass function this.
You can use either definition.
Let me just make sure that I
didn't mess up in the middle.
Yes.
And that only works
for x greater than 0.
Yes?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]?
PROFESSOR: Yeah.
So all logs are natural log.
It should be ln.
Yeah.
Thank you.
OK.
So question-- what's the mean
of this distribution here?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: 1?
PROFESSOR: Not 1.
It might be mu.
Is it mu?
Oh, sorry.
It might be e to the mu.
Because log X, the normal
distribution had mean mu.
log x equals mu
might be the center.
If that's the case, x is e
to the mu will be the mean.
Is that the case?
Yes?
AUDIENCE: Can you get
the mu minus [INAUDIBLE]?
PROFESSOR: Probably right.
I don't remember what's there.
There is a correcting factor.
I don't remember
exactly what that is,
but I think you're right.
So one very important
thing to remember
is log-normal
distribution are referred
to in terms of the
parameters mu and sigma,
because that's the mu and
sigma up here and here coming
from the normal distribution.
But those are not the
mean and variance anymore,
because you skew
the distribution.
It's no longer centered at mu.
log X is centered at mu, but
when it takes exponential,
it becomes skewed.
And we take the average,
you'll see that the mean
is no longer e to the mu.
So that doesn't give the mean.
That doesn't imply that
the mean is e to the sigma.
That doesn't imply
that the variance is
something like e to the sigma.
That's just totally nonsense.
Just remember-- these are just
parameters, some parameters.
It's no longer mean or variance.
And in your homework,
one exercise,
we'll ask you to compute
the mean and variance
of the random variable.
But really, just try to
have it stick in your mind
that mu and sigma is no
longer mean and variance.
That's only the case for
normal random variables.
And the reason we are
still using mu and sigma
is because of this derivation.
And it's easy to
describe it in those.
OK.
So the normal distribution
and log-normal distribution
will probably be
the distributions
that you'll see the most
throughout the course.
But there are some
other distributions
that you'll also see.
I need this.
I will not talk
about it in detail.
It will be some
exercise questions.
For example, you have Poisson
distribution or exponential
distributions.
These are some other
distributions that you'll see.
And all of these-- normal,
log-normal, Poisson,
and exponential,
and a lot more can
be grouped into a
family of distributions
called exponential family.
So a distribution is called to
be in an exponential family--
A distribution belongs
to exponential family
if there exists a theta,
a vector that parametrizes
the distribution such that
the probability density
function for this choice
of parameter theta
can be written as h
of x times c of theta
times the exponent of
sum from i equal 1 to k--
Yes.
So here, when I write
only x, h should only
depend on x, not on theta.
When I write some
function of theta,
it should only depend
on theta, not on x.
So h(x), t_i(x) depends only
on x and c(theta) on my value
theta, depends only on theta.
That's an abstract thing.
It's not clear why
this is so useful,
at least from the definition.
But you're going to talk
about some distribution
for an exponential
family, right?
Yeah.
So you will see
something about this.
But one good thing
is, they exhibit
some good statistical
behavior, the things-- when
you group them into--
all distributions
in the exponential family
have some nice statistical
properties, which makes it good.
That's too abstract.
Let's see how log-normal
distribution actually falls
into the exponential family.
AUDIENCE: So, let
me just comment.
PROFESSOR: Yeah, sure.
AUDIENCE: The notion of
independent random variables,
you went over how the--
well, the probability density
functions of collections
of random variables
if they're mutually
independent is
the product of the
probability densities
of the individual variables.
And so with this
exponential family,
if you have random variables
from the same exponential
family, products of this
density function factor out
into a very simple form.
It doesn't get more
complicated as you
look at the joint density
of many variables,
and in fact simplifies to
the same exponential family.
So that's where that
becomes very useful.
PROFESSOR: So it's designed
so that it factors out
when it's multiplied.
It factors out well.
OK.
So-- sorry about that.
Yeah, log-normal distribution.
So take h(x), 1 over x.
Before that, let's just rewrite
that in a different way.
So 1 over x sigma square
root 2 pi, e to the minus log
x [INAUDIBLE] squared.
Square.
Can be rewritten as 1
over x, times 1 over sigma
squared 2 pi, e to
the minus log x square
over 2 sigma square plus
mu log x over sigma square
minus mu square.
Let's write it like that.
Set up h(x) equals 1 over x.
c of theta-- sorry,
theta equals mu sigma.
c(theta) is equal to 1 over
sigma square root 2 pi, e
to the minus mu square.
So you will
parametrize this family
in terms of mu and sigma.
Your h of x here
will be 1 over x.
Your c(theta) will be this
term and the last term here,
because this
doesn't depend on x.
And then you have to
figure out what w and t is.
You can let w_1 of
x be log x square.
t_1-- no, t_1 of x be log x
square, w_1 of theta be minus 1
over 2 sigma square.
And similarly, you
can let t_2 equals log
x and w_2 equals mu over sigma.
It's just some technicality,
but at least you
can see it really fits in.
OK.
So that's all
about distributions
that I want to talk about.
And then let's talk
a little bit more
about more interesting
stuff, in my opinion.
I like this stuff better.
There are two main things
that we're interested in.
When we have a random variable,
at least for our purpose, what
we want to study is given
a random variable, first,
we want to study a statistics.
So we want to study this
statistics, whatever
that means.
And that will be represented
by the k-th moments
of the random variable.
Where k-th moment is defined
as expectation of X to the k.
And a good way to study
all the moments together
in one function is a
moment-generating function.
So this moment-generating
function
encodes all the k-th moments
of a random variable.
So it contains all the
statistical information
of a random variable.
That's why
moment-generating function
will be interesting to us.
Because when you
want to study it,
you don't have to consider
each moment separately.
It gives a unified way.
It gives a very good
feeling about your function.
That will be our first topic.
Our second topic will
be we want to study
its long-term or
large-scale behavior.
So for example, assume that you
have a normal distribution--
one random variable with
normal distribution.
If we just have a
single random variable,
you really have no control.
It can be anywhere.
The outcome can be anything
according to that distribution.
But if you have several
independent random variables
with the exact
same distribution,
if the number is super large--
let's say 100 million--
and you plot how many random
variables fall into each point
into a graph,
you'll know that it
has to look very
close to this curve.
It will be more dense
here, sparser there,
and sparser there.
So you don't have
individual control on each
of the random variables.
But when you look
at large scale,
you know, at least with
very high probability,
it has to look like this curve.
Those kind of things are
what we want to study.
When we look at this long-term
behavior or large scale
behavior, what can we say?
What kind of events
are guaranteed
to happen with probability,
let's say, 99.9%?
And actually, some interesting
things are happening.
As you might already know, two
typical theorems of this type
will be, in this
topic will be law
of large numbers and
central limit theorem.
So let's start with
our first topic--
the moment-generating function.
The moment-generating
function of a random variable
is defined as-- I
write it as m sub
X. It's defined as expectation
of e to the t times x
where t is some parameter.
t can be any real.
You have to be careful.
It doesn't always converge.
So remark: does not
necessarily exist.
So for example, one of the
distributions you already saw
does not have
moment-generating function.
The log-normal
distribution does not
have any moment-generating
function.
And that's one thing
you have to be careful.
It's not just some
theoretical thing.
The statement is not
something theoretical.
It actually happens for
some random variables
that you encounter in your life.
So be careful.
And that will actually show
some very interesting thing
I will later explain.
Some very interesting
facts arise from this fact.
Before going into
that, first of all,
why is it called
moment-generating function?
It's because if you
take the k-th derivative
of this function,
then it actually
gives the k-th moment
of your random variable.
That's where the
name comes from.
It's for all integers.
And that gives a
different way of writing
a moment-generating function.
Because of that, we may write
the moment-generating function
as the sum from k equals
0 to infinity, t to the k,
k factorial, times
a k-th moment.
That's like the
Taylor expansion.
Because you know
all the derivatives,
you know what the
functions would be.
Of course, only if it exists.
This might not converge.
So if moment-generating
function exists,
they pretty much classify
your random variables.
So if two random
variables, X, Y,
have the same
moment-generating function,
then X and Y have the
same distribution.
I will not prove this theorem.
But it says that
moment-generating function,
if it exists, encodes
really all the information
about your random variables.
You're not losing anything.
However, be very careful when
you're applying this theorem.
Because remark,
it does not imply
that all random variables
with identical k-th moments
for all k has the
same distribution.
Do you see it?
If X and Y have a
moment-generating function,
and they're the same, then they
have the same distribution.
This looks a little bit
controversial to this theorem.
It says that it's not
necessarily the case
that two random variables, which
have identical moments-- so
all k-th moments are the
same for two variables--
even if that's the case,
they don't necessarily
have to have the
same distribution.
Which seems like it
doesn't make sense
if you look at this theorem.
Because moment-generating
function
is defined in terms
of the moments.
If two random variables
have the same moment,
we have the same
moment-generating function.
If they have the same
moment-generating function,
they have the same distribution.
There is a hole
in this argument.
Even if they have
the same moments,
it doesn't necessarily
imply that they
have the same
moment-generating function.
They might both not have
moment-generating functions.
That's the glitch.
Be careful.
So just remember that even if
they have the same moments,
they don't necessarily
have the same distribution.
And the reason is
because-- one reason
is because the moment-generating
function might not exist.
And if you look in
to Wikipedia, you'll
see an example of
when it happens,
of two random variables
where this happens.
So that's one thing
we will use later.
Another thing that
we will use later,
it's a statement
very similar to that,
but it says something about a
sequence of random variables.
So if X_1, X_2, up to X_n is
a sequence of random variables
such that the moment-generating
function exists,
and it converges-- ah,
it goes to infinity.
Tends to the
moment-generating function
of some random variable t.
X. For some random
variable X for all t.
Here, we're assuming that all
moment-generating function
exists.
So again, the
situation is, you have
a sequence of random variables.
Their moment-generating
function exists.
And in each point
t, it converges
to the value of the
moment-generating function
of some other random variable x.
And what should happen?
In light of this theorem,
it should be the case
that the distribution
of this sequence
gets closer and closer
to the distribution
of this random variable x.
And to make it formal, to make
that information formal, what
we can conclude is, for
all x, the probability
X_i is less than or equal to
x tends to the probability
that at x.
So in this sense,
the distributions
of these random variables
converges to the distribution
of that random variable.
So it's just a technical issue.
You can just think of it as
these random variables converge
to that random variable.
If you take some graduate
probability course,
you'll see that there's
several possible ways
to define convergence.
But that's just
some technicality.
And the spirit
here is just really
the sequence converges if its
moment-generating function
converges.
So as you can see from
these two theorems,
moment-generating
function, if it exists,
is a really powerful
tool that allows you
to control the distribution.
You'll see some applications
later in central limit theorem.
Any questions?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]?
PROFESSOR: This one?
Why?
AUDIENCE: Because
it starts with t,
and the right-hand side
has nothing general.
PROFESSOR: Ah.
Thank you.
We evaluated at zero.
Other questions?
Other corrections?
AUDIENCE: When you say the
moment-generating function
doesn't exist, do you mean
that it isn't analytic
or it doesn't converge?
PROFESSOR: It
might not converge.
So log-normal distribution,
it does not converge.
So for all non-zero
t, it does not
converge, for
log-normal distribution.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]?
PROFESSOR: Here?
Yes.
Pointwise convergence implies
pointwise convergence.
No, no.
Because it's pointwise, this
conclusion is also rather weak.
It's almost the weakest
convergence in distribution.
OK.
The law of large numbers.
So now we're talking about
large-scale behavior.
Let X_1 up to X_n be
independent random variables
with identical distribution.
We don't really know
what the distribution is,
but we know that
they're all the same.
In short, I'll just refer
to this condition as i.i.d.
random variables later.
Independent, identically
distributed random variables.
And let mean be mu,
variance be sigma square.
Let's also define X as the
average of n random variables.
Then the probability that--
X-- for all-- all positive
[INAUDIBLE].
So whenever you have identical
independent distributions, when
you take their average, if
you take a large enough number
of samples, they will be
very close to the mean, which
makes sense.
So what's an example of this?
Before proving it, example
of this theorem in practice
can be seen in the casino.
So for example, if
you're playing blackjack
in a casino, when you're
playing against the casino,
you have a very
small disadvantage.
If you're playing at
the optimal strategy,
you have-- does anybody
know the probability?
It's about 48%, 49%.
About 48% chance of winning.
That means if you bet $1 at
the beginning of each round,
the expected amount
you'll win is $0.48.
The expected amount that the
casino will win is $0.52.
But it's designed so
that the variance is
so big that this expectation
is hidden, the mean is hidden.
From the player's
point of view, you only
have a very small sample.
So it looks like the
mean doesn't matter,
because the variance takes
over in a very short scale.
But from the casino's
point of view,
they're taking a
very large n there.
So for each round, let's
say from the casino's
point of view, it's
like taking, they
are taking enormous value of n.
n here.
And that means as long as they
have the slightest advantage,
they'll be winning money,
and a huge amount of money.
And most games played in the
casinos are designed like this.
It looks like the mean
is really close to 50%,
but it's hidden,
because they designed it
so the variance is big.
But from the casino's
point of view,
they have enough
players to play the game
so that the law of large
numbers just makes them money.
The moral is, don't
play blackjack.
Play poker.
The reason that the rule
of law of large numbers
doesn't apply, at least
in this sense, to poker--
can anybody explain why?
It's because poker, you're
playing against other players.
If you have an advantage, if
your skill-- if you believe
that there is skill in poker--
if your skill is better
than the other
player by, let's say,
5% chance, then you have
an edge over that player.
So you can win money.
The only problem is that
because-- poker, you're
not playing against the casino.
Don't play against casino.
But they still
have to make money.
So what they do instead
is they take rake.
So for each round
that the players play,
they pay some fee to the casino.
And how the casino makes
money at the poker table
is by accumulating those fees.
They're not taking
chances there.
But from the player's
point of view,
if you're better than the other
player, and the amount of edge
you have over the other
player is larger than the fee
that the casino
charges to you, then
now you can apply law of large
numbers to yourself and win.
And if you take an
example as poker,
it looks like-- OK, I'm
not going to play poker.
But if it's a hedge
fund, or if you're
doing high-frequency trading,
that's the moral behind it.
So that's the belief
you should have.
You have to believe
that you have an edge.
Even if you have a
tiny edge, if you
can have enough
number of trials,
if you can trade enough of times
using some strategy that you
believe is winning over time,
then law of large numbers
will take it from there and
will bring you money, profit.
Of course, the problem is,
when the variance is big,
your belief starts to fall.
At least, that was the case for
me when I was playing poker.
Because I believed
that I had an edge,
but when there is
really swing, it
looks like your
expectation is negative.
And that's when you have
to believe in yourself.
Yeah.
That's when your
faith in mathematics
is being challenged.
It really happened.
I hope it doesn't happen to you.
Anyway, that's proof
law of large numbers.
How do you prove it?
The proof is quite easy.
First of all, one observation--
expectation of X is just
expectation of 1 over
n times sum of X_i's.
And that, by linearity,
just becomes the sum of--
and that's mu.
OK.
That's good.
And then the variance,
what's the variance of X?
That's the expectation
of X minus mu
square, which is the expectation
sum over all i's, minus mu
square.
I'll group them.
That's the expectation of 1 over
n sum of X_i minus mu square.
i is from 1 to n.
What did I do wrong?
1 over n is inside the square.
So I can take it out
and square, n square.
And then you're summing
n terms of sigma square.
So that is equal to
sigma square over n.
That means the
effect of averaging
n terms does not
affect your average,
but it affects your variance.
It divides your variance by n.
If you take larger and
larger n, your variance
gets smaller and smaller.
And using that, we can
prove this statement.
There's only one thing
you have to notice--
that the probability
that x minus mu
is greater than epsilon.
When you multiply this
by epsilon square.
This will be less than or
equal to the variance of x.
The reason this
inequality holds is
because variance X is defined
as the expectation of X minus mu
square.
For all the events when you have
X minus mu at least epsilon,
your multiplying
factor X square will
be at least epsilon square.
This term will be at
least epsilon square
when you fall into this event.
So your variance has
to be at least that.
And this is known to
be sigma square over n.
So probability that
x minus mu is greater
than epsilon is at most sigma
square over n epsilon squared.
That means if you take n to go
to infinity, that goes to zero.
So the probability that
you deviate from the mean
by more than epsilon goes to 0.
You can actually read out a
little bit more from the proof.
It also tells a little bit
about the speed of convergence.
So let's say you have a random
variable X. Your mean is 50.
You epsilon is 0.1.
So you want to know
the probability
that you deviate from your
mean by more than 0.1.
Let's say you want
to be 99% sure.
Want to be 99% sure that X
minus mu is less than 0.1,
or X minus 50 is less than 0.1.
In that case, what you can do
is-- you want this to be 0.01.
It has to be 0.01.
So plug in that, plug in your
variance, plug in your epsilon.
That will give you
some bound on n.
If you have more than
that number of trials,
you can be 99% sure that you
don't deviate from your mean
by more than epsilon.
So that does give
some estimate, but I
should mention that this
is a very bad estimate.
There are much more
powerful estimates
that can be done here.
That will give the order of
magnitude-- I didn't really
calculate here, but it looks
like it's close to millions.
It has to be close to millions.
But in practice, if you use
a lot more powerful tool
of estimating it, it should
only be hundreds or at most
thousands.
So the tool you'll use there
is moment-generating functions,
something similar to
moment-generating functions.
But I will not go into it.
Any questions?
OK.
For those who already saw
law of large numbers before,
the name suggests there's
also something called
strong law of large numbers.
In that theorem, your
conclusion is stronger.
So the convergence is stronger
than this type of convergence.
And also, the
condition I gave here
is a very strong condition.
The same conclusion
is true even if you
weaken some of the conditions.
So for example, the variance
does not have to exist.
It can be replaced by some
other condition, and so on.
But here, I just want
it to be a simple form
so that it's easy to prove.
And you at least get the
spirit of what's happening.
Now let's move on to the next
topic-- central limit theorem.
So weak law of
large numbers says
that if you have IID random
variables, 1 over n times
sum over X_i's converges to mu,
the mean, in some weak sense.
And the reason it happened
was because this had
mean mu and variance
sigma square over n.
We've exploited the fact that
variance vanishes to get this.
So the question is, what
happens if you replace 1 over n
by 1 over square root n?
What happens if-- for
the random variable
1 over square root n times X_i?
The reason I'm making this
choice of 1 over square root n
is because if you
make this choice,
now the average has mean mu
and variance sigma square just
as in X_i's.
So this is the same as X_i.
Then what should it look like?
If the random variable is the
same mean and same variance
as your original random
variable, the distribution
of this, should it look like
the distribution of X_i?
If mean is mu.
Thank you very much.
The case when mean is 0.
OK.
For this special case,
will it look like X_i,
or will it not look like X_i?
If it doesn't look like X_i,
can we say anything interesting
about the distribution of this?
And central limit theorem
answers this question.
When I first saw it, I thought
it was really interesting.
Because normal
distribution comes up here.
And that's probably
one of the reasons
that normal distribution
is so universal.
Because when you take
many independent events
and take the average
in this sense,
their distribution converges
to a normal distribution.
Yes?
AUDIENCE: How did you get
mean equals [INAUDIBLE]?
PROFESSOR: I didn't get it.
I assumed it if X-- yeah.
So theorem: let
X_1, X_2, to X_n be
IID random variables with mean,
this time, mu and variance
sigma squared.
And let X-- or Y_n.
Y_n be square root n times
1 over n, of X_i minus mu.
Then the distribution
of Y_n converges
to that of normal distribution
with mean 0 and variance sigma.
What this means-- I'll
write it down again--
it means for all x,
probability that Y_n
is less than or
equal to x converges
the probability that normal
distribution is less than
or equal to x.
What's really
interesting here is,
no matter what distribution
you had in the beginning,
if we average it
out in this sense,
then you converge to
the normal distribution.
Any questions about this
statement, or any corrections?
Any mistakes that I made?
OK.
Here's the proof.
I will prove it when the
moment-generating function
exists.
So assume that the
moment-generating functions
exists.
So proof assuming
m of X_i exists.
So remember that theorem.
Try to recall that
theorem where if you
know that the moment-generating
function of Y_n's converges
to the moment-generating
function of the normal, then
we have the statement.
The distribution converges.
So that's the statement
we're going to use.
That means our goal is to prove
that the moment-generating
function of these Y_n's converge
to the moment-generating
function of the normal for
all t, pointwise convergence.
And this part is well known.
I'll just write it down.
It's known to be e to the t
square sigma square over 2.
That just can be computed.
So we want to somehow show that
the moment-generating function
of this Y_n converges to that.
The moment-generating
function of Y_n
is equal to expectation
of e to t Y_n.
e to the t, 1 over square
root n, sum of X_i minus mu.
And then because each of
the X_i's are independent,
this sum will split
into products.
Product of-- let
me split it better.
Meets the expectation-- we
didn't use independent yet.
Sum becomes products of e to
the t, 1 over square root n, X_i
minus mu.
And then because
they're independent,
this product can go out.
Equal to the product from 1 to
n expectation e to the t times
square root n--
OK.
Now they're identically
distributed,
so you just have to take
the n-th power of that.
That's equal to the
expectation of e
to the t over square root n,
X_i minus mu, to the n-th power.
Now we'll do some estimation.
So use the Taylor
expansion of this.
What we get is expectation of 1
plus that, t over square root n
xi minus mu, plus 1 over
2 factorial, that squared,
t over square root n,
xi minus mu squared,
plus 1 over 3 factorial,
that cubed plus so on.
Then that's equal to 1--
Ah, to the n-th power.
The linearity of
expectation, 1 comes out.
Second term is 0,
because X_i have mean mu.
So that disappears.
This term-- we have 1 over 2,
t squared over n, X_i minus mu
square.
X_i minus mu square, when
you take expectation,
that will be sigma square.
And then the terms after
that, because we're
only interested in
proving that for fixed t,
this converges-- so we're only
proving pointwise convergence.
You may consider t
as a fixed number.
So as n goes to infinity--
if n is really, really large,
all these terms will be
smaller order of magnitude
than n, 1 over n.
Something like that happens.
And that's happening
because we're fixed.
For fixed t, we
have to prove it.
So if we're saying
something uniformly about t,
that's no longer true.
Now we go back to
the exponential form.
So this is pretty much
just e to that term,
1 over 2 t square
sigma square over n
plus little o of 1 over
n to the n-th power.
Now, that n can be
multiplied to cancel out.
And we see that it's e to t
square sigma square over 2
plus the little o of 1.
So if you take n
to go to infinity,
that term disappears,
and we prove
that it converges to that.
And then by the theorem that I
stated before, if we have this,
we know that the
distribution converges.
Any questions?
OK.
I'll make one final remark.
So suppose there is a random
variable x whose mean we do not
know, whose mean is unknown.
Our goal is to
estimate the mean.
And one way to do that is by
taking many independent trials
of this random variable.
So take independent trials X_1,
X_2, to X_n, and use 1 over--
X_1 plus...
X_n as our estimator.
Then the law of large
numbers says that this
will be very close to the mean.
So if you take n
to be large enough,
you will more than likely
have some value which
is very close to the mean.
And then the central
limit theorem
tells you how the
distribution of this variable
is around the mean.
So we don't know what
the real value is,
but we know that
the distribution
of the value that
we will obtain here
is something like
that around the mean.
And because normal distribution
have very small tails,
the tail distributions
is really small,
we will get really
close really fast.
And this is known as the maximum
likelihood estimator, is it?
OK, yeah.
For some distributions,
it's better
to take some other estimator.
Which is quite interesting.
At least my intuition is to
take this for every single case,
looks like that will
be a good choice.
But it turns out that
that's not the case;
for some distributions there's
a better choice than this.
And Peter will
later talk about it.
If you're interested
in, come back.
And that's it for
today, any questions?
So next Tuesday we will
have an outside speaker,
and it will be on bonds.
and I don't think anything from
linear algebra will be here.